Guide to the Jeffrey Gerson Brooklyn politics research collection 2013.021
Brooklyn Historical Society
- Murray Feiden, circa 1989 (Box 2, Folder 22, Box 9, Cassette 2, Cassette 25)
  Murray T. Feiden was born on December 7, 1904 in Philadelphia, Pennsylvania. His family moved to Brooklyn in 1910. Feiden was a justice of the City Court of New York and a justice of the Supreme Court of the State of New York. He was a founding member of Common Cause and a member of the 18th Assembly District Madison Democratic Club. He died on May 10, 2008.
  This interview took place on February 13, 1988. This interview is not accompanied by a transcript.
  One preservation .WAV files. One access .mp3 file.
- Harold Fisher, 1987 (Box 2, Folder 23, Box 9, Cassette 3)
  Harold Leonard Fisher was born on December 10, 1910 in the Lower East Side neighborhood of Manhattan. He received his law degree from St. John's University College of Law in 1932 and opened up a law practice in 1935 in Manhattan. He moved the practice to Downtown Brooklyn in 1948. He was a delegate to the New York State Constitutional Convention in 1967. Governor Nelson A. Rockefeller appointed him to the Metropolitan Transit Authority board in 1968 and served on the board in different positions through 1979. He died on December 26, 1999.
  This interview took place on August 1, 1985 in Harold Fisher's law office. This interview is accompanied by a transcript.
- Lewis Flagg, 1954-1955 (Box 2, Folder 24)
- Sylvia Frank, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 25, Box 9, Cassette 4)
  Sylvia Frank was born in 1921. She was active in Brooklyn's 41st Assembly District and was president of the parent-teacher association at P.S. 244.
  This interview took place on June 7, 1984. Jeffrey Gerson conducted this interview with Sylvia Frank while he was a research assistant for Professor Sharon Zukin of Brooklyn College and Gilda Zwerman of The State University of New York - Westbury. From this project they published: "Housing for the Working Poor: A Historical View of Jews and Blacks in Brownsville," New York Affairs 9 (1985). This interview is not accompanied by a transcript.
- Narcissus Frett-Moses, 1992 (Box 2, Folder 26, Box 9, Cassette 5)
  Narcissus Frett-Moses was born on August 20, 1929 in Brooklyn, New York. She was active in the Unity Democratic Club under the leadership of Thomas Russell Jones and Ruth Goring from 1960-1964. She worked for Shirley Chisholm during her political career. She also served as Deputy Chief Clerk of the Surrogates Court from 1968-1989. Frett-Moses died in 2022.
  This interview took place on March 26, 1992 in the Surrogates Office of the State Supreme Court in Brooklyn. This interview is not accompanied by a transcript.
- Milton Friedman, 1989 (Box 2, Folder 27)
- Donna Gabaccia, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 28)
- Jeannette Gadson, 1993 (Box 2, Folder 29)
- Milton Galamison, 1965-1969 (Box 2, Folder 30)
- William Garry, 1987 (Box 2, Folder 31, Box 9, Cassette 6)
  This interview took place on September 16, 1987. This interview is accompanied by a transcript.
  William J. Garry was born on August 8, 1929 in the Sunset Park neighborhood of Brooklyn. His parents had emigrated from Ireland. He was campaign manager for Jack Murphy for Congress in 1960. He ran for positions in the New York State Assembly and New York State Senate for the 9th Assembly District, but did not win. He was a justice of the New York Supreme Court from 1986 to 2003. He was secretary of the Brooklyn Democratic Party and an alternate delegate to the Democratic National Convention from New York in 1980. Garry died on June 11, 2009.
- Simon Gerson [and Sophie Melvin Gerson], circa 1989 (Box 2, Folder 32, Box 9, Cassette 7, Cassette 8)
  Simon "Si" Gerson was born on January 23, 1909 in Manhattan. He attended the City College of New York where he met labor activist Sophie Melvin. They married in 1932. Gerson was a reporter and editor for the Daily Worker. In 1937, Gerson was appointed to be Manhattan Borough President Stanley M. Isaac's executive assistant. Gerson served in the U.S. Army in the Pacific theater in World War II. He then managed Communist candidate Peter Cacchione's campaign for New York City Council. Cacchione served from 1941 to 1947 when he died from a heart attack. Gerson was named to fill in Cacchione's seat, but then was forced to run in a borough-wide race. He was endorsed by the American Labor Party and the Communist Party and won the election. He died on December 26, 2004.
  Simon Gerson and Jeffrey Gerson are not related.
  Sophie Gerson, née Melvin, was born on February 22, 1910 in Ukraine. Gerson and her family moved to the Brownsville neighborhood of Brooklyn and Gerson started volunteering to support striking workers when she was a teenager. She became a member of the Young Communist League and was a relief worker during the Great Depression, helping organize a demonstration of 100,000 unemployed people in Union Square. In 1948, the Gersons moved to Bensonhurst, Brooklyn where they lived for the rest of their lives. Sophie and Simon Gerson had two children, William and Deborah. Later in her life, Gerson was active in the National Council of Senior Citizens. Sophie Gerson died on March 20, 2006.
  This interview took place on February 10, 1988 at the Gersons' residence in the Bensonhurst neighborhood of Brooklyn. Sophie Gerson, Simon Gerson's wife, is also a part of this interview. This interview is not accompanied by a transcript.
  Related Materials
  The Tamiment Library and Wagner Labor Archives holds the following related materials:
  - Sophie M. Gerson Papers, 1929-2009 (TAM.401)
  - Simon W. and Sophie Gerson Papers, 1925-2001 (TAM.330)
- Marvin E. Gettleman, 1977-1982 (Box 2, Folder 33)
- Marilyn Gittell, 1971 (Box 2, Folder 34)
- Merel J. Pomeranz Glaubiger, circa 1963 (Box 2, Folder 35)
  This file contains a student paper titled "Hymie Schorenstein - A Political Biography."
- Milton Goldner, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 36 - 37, Box 9, Cassette 9, Cassette 10, Cassette 11, Cassette 12, Cassette 13)
  Milton Goldner was born in 1926. He was active in Brooklyn and Manhattan politics since 1952. He died in 2002.
  This interview took place in three parts on March 18, 1988, March 21, 1988, and March 23, 1988 in a Kings Highway diner and outdoors in a park. This interview is accompanied by a transcript.
  Seven preservation .WAV files. Seven access .mp3 files.
- Arnold Goldwag, 1993 (Box 2, Folder 38, Box 9, Cassette 14)
  Arnold "Arnie" Stanley Goldwag was born on January 18, 1938. A resident of Brooklyn, Goldwag attended Brooklyn College beginning in 1955 where he held leadership positions in a range of organizations, including social fraternities, student government, and student rights groups. He left Brooklyn College about 1961 without graduating, though he was readmitted in 1966 and graduated in 1968.
  While still at Brooklyn College in the late 1950s, Goldwag became involved in the activities of the Brooklyn chapter of the Congress of Racial Equality (CORE), starting with distributing fliers urging a boycott of Woolworth's. His role in the chapter expanded quickly, and in the years of Goldwag's active participation in CORE (1960-1965), he held leadership positions, principally as the Community Relations Director. In this position, Goldwag was responsible for press relations, publicity, and coordination with communities and demonstrators on the organization's direct actions. Over the course of his tenure in Brooklyn CORE, Goldwag participated in a number of actions, both locally, such as the 1963 Board of Education sit-in, and nationally, such as in Cambridge, Maryland, where Goldwag was involved in CORE's effort to desegregate public facilities. Goldwag's activism led to several arrests and a 13 month prison sentence in 1964; he served one month of the sentence in Rikers Island penitentiary.
  Founded in Chicago in 1942, CORE was centered on the principles of interracial, nonviolent direct action. Local chapters that affiliated with national CORE had a great deal of autonomy of action. Within this structure, Brooklyn CORE emerged in the early 1960s as one of the most radical CORE chapters, focusing on the living conditions of poor African-Americans in Bedford-Stuyvesant and employing increasingly aggressive confrontational tactics. It was during this surging radical activism in Brooklyn CORE that Goldwag was a central figure in the chapter and in its many civil rights actions. Indeed, Goldwag was a principal creator of one of Brooklyn CORE's most controversial actions, the Stall-In at the opening of the 1964 World's Fair. This action, which called for the deliberate blockage of automobile traffic headed to the Fair in order to call attention to discrimination against African-Americans, led to the suspension of the chapter by CORE.
  Subsequent to his days with CORE, which ended in 1965, and his 1968 graduation from Brooklyn College, Goldwag went to work for the New York City Human Resources Administration as a contract manager for home care programs. In the 1990s he went on leave to work for his union (Social Service Employees Union Local 371) as Health and Safety Coordinator. In the 1990s and 2000s, Goldwag was actively engaged in ensuring that the civil rights movement was remembered, and its continued struggle recognized. He participated in a number of conferences and oral histories, and opened his files to researchers. Arnie Goldwag died on August 9, 2008.
  This interview took place on May 27, 1993. This interview is not accompanied by a transcript.
- Ruth Goring, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 39 - 40)
  Ruth Goring was born on July 19, 1919 in East Harlem in Manhattan. She was a member and co-leader of the Unity Democratic Club in Brooklyn. Goring and Thomas R. Jones ran for district leadership in 1960 and lost. They won when they ran again in 1962. She died in 2006.
  This interview took place on April 28, 1988. This interview is accompanied by a transcript.
  Access to the interview is available digitally onsite at Center for Brooklyn History's Othmer Library.
- Jesse Gray, 1964-1965 (Box 2, Folder 41)
- George Gregory, Jr., 1960-1990 (Box 2, Folder 42)
- Edward Griffith, circa 1987 (Box 2, Folder 43)
- Margaret Groarke, 1993 (Box 2, Folder 44)
  This file contains a paper by Margaret Groarke titled "Who was Empowered? Decentralization of the New York Public Schools."
- Haryou Anti-Poverty Association, 1964-1967 (Box 2, Folder 45)
- John F. Hayes, 1987 (Box 3, Folder 1, Box 9, Cassette 15, Box 10, Cassette 26)
  John F. Hayes was born in Brooklyn in 1915. He attended Brooklyn Preparatory School, Fordham College, and Fordham Law School. He was an agent for the Federal Bureau of Investigation (FBI) from 1943 to 1950. In 1948, John F. Hayes married Margaret Sullivan. After working as an FBI agent, Hayes became an assistant for Brooklyn Borough President John Cashmore and then Brooklyn's Commissioner of Public Works. When John Cashmore died in office in 1961, Hayes became acting borough president and then was elected by the New York City Council to continue as interim borough president until the end of 1961. He was elected to the New York State Supreme Court in 1977 and served until his retirement in 1984.
  This interview took place on October 21, 1987. The interview includes an elevator conversation with strangers and was conducted partially outside. This interview is accompanied by a transcript.
- Joseph H. Helfgot, 1981 (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Louis Heller, 1987 (Box 3, Folder 3, Box 9, Cassette 16, Cassette 17)
  Louis "Louie" Benjamin Heller was born on the Lower East Side of Manhattan on February 7, 1905. He lived much of his life in Williamsburg and Bedford-Stuyvesant in Brooklyn and went to Boys High School. He received his law degree from Fordham University in 1926. Heller was active in the Democratic party in Brooklyn and held several positions in political office and the courts. He served as a New York State Senator from Brooklyn from 1943-1944, a Democratic Congressman from Brooklyn from 1949-1954, and on the State Supreme Court in the 1960s and 1970s. Heller died of colon cancer on October 30, 1993.
  This interview took place on October 7, 1987 at a restaurant and outdoors in the Brooklyn Heights neighborhood of Brooklyn. This interview is accompanied by a transcript.
- Lloyd Herzka, 1958 (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Gregory Hesterberg, 1956-1971 (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Gregory Hesterberg, 1987 (Box 3, Folder 6, Box 9, Cassette 18)
  Gregory X. Hesterberg is an attorney. At the time of the interview, he was with the firm Alexander Hesterberg and Keller on 32 Court Street, 21st floor.
  Gregory Hesterberg's great grandfather, Henry Hesterberg, was the district leader of Flatbush in the late 1880s until the 1910s. Henry Hesterberg was the first Democrat elected to county-wide office in 1903 (as Sheriff) until 1909, according to Gregory Hesterberg. He was also the Flatbush Democratic district leader in 1918.
  Gregory Hesterberg's grandfather, Henry Hesterberg, Jr., was Brooklyn borough president from 1930 to 1933.
  This interview took place on August 19, 1987 at Gregory Hesterberg's law office. This interview is accompanied by a transcript.
- Hesterberg clippings, 1933-1971 (Box 3, Folder 7)
- Wesley McDonald Holder, 1962-1989 (Box 3, Folder 8, Box 9, Cassette 19)
  Wesley "Mac" McDonald Holder was born on June 24, 1897 in Guyana and moved to Bedford-Stuyvesant in Brooklyn in the 1920s to join Marcus Garvey's Universal Negro Improvement Association.
  Holder was known as the "Dean of Black Politics" and managed many successful campaigns including Lewis S. Flagg, Jr.'s campaign for Brooklyn Municipal Court judge in 1953. As a result of this campaign, Flagg became the first Black judge elected in Brooklyn. Holder also worked on Shirley Chisholm's campaign for Congress and worked in her Brooklyn office for over a decade.
  Holder died of pneumonia in March 1993.
  This interview took place on June 21, 1989 in Brooklyn. This interview is not accompanied by a transcript.
- Harold Jacobs, circa 1989 (Box 3, Folder 9, Box 9, Cassette 20)
  Biographical / Historical
  Harold Jacobs was born on October 25, 1912 in the Williamsburg neighborhood of Brooklyn. He was then raised in Crown Heights and went to Boys High School. He received his undergraduate degree from St. John's University and his master's degree in economics from Columbia University.
  Jacobs was a businessman; he started a kitchenware company called Precision Ware and also headed an investment company called Precision Equities. He held board roles in civic and religious organizations. Mayor Abraham Beame appointed him to the Board of Higher Education in 1974 and he was head of the Union of Orthodox Jewish Congregations of America. He died on May 18, 1995.
  This interview took place on February 1, 1988 at Harold Jacobs office at 295 Madison Avenue in Manhattan. This interview is not accompanied by a transcript.
- Madison S. Jonas, 1954-1963 (Box 3, Folder 10)
- J. Raymond Jones, 1947-1967 (Box 3, Folder 11)
- J. Raymond Jones, 1991 (Box 3, Folder 12)
- Thomas Russell Jones, 1987-1993 (Box 3, Folder 13-15, Box 9, Cassette 21, Cassette 22, Cassette 23, Cassette 24)
  Thomas "Tom" Russell Jones was born on August 5, 1913 in Brooklyn to Thomas S. Jones and Mabel Ward Jones who had emigrated from Barbados. He received undergraduate and law degrees from St. John's University. Jones married Bertha K. Jones in 1941. He was in the U.S. Army during World War II in France.
  When he returned from the War, Jones continued his work in politics and civil rights activism. He was elected to the New York State Assembly in 1962 and also served as a judge on the Civil Court and State Supreme Court. Jones was also a founding chairman of the Bedford-Stuyvesant Restoration Corporation.
  Jones retired from the court in 1985. He died of prostate cancer on October 27, 2006.
  Thomas R. Jones was interviewed twice by Jeffrey Gerson, once on July 28, 1987 and once on July 15, 1993. The first interview lasted only two minutes on tape, but Gerson took notes of the rest of the interview. Gerson requested a second interview and was granted one in 1993.
  Audio related to this interview includes Jeffrey Gerson's comments after the interview. This interview is accompanied by a partial transcript.
  Jeffrey Gerson's audio comments are one one access .mp3 file. There is no preservation .WAV file.
- William Augustus Jones, Jr., 1963-1988 (Box 3, Folder 16)
- Anthony Jordan, Jr., 1989 (Box 3, Folder 17, Box 9, Cassette 25, Cassette 26)
  Anthony T. Jordan, Jr. was born on June 26, 1924 in Crown Heights in Brooklyn. He was a former member of the 18th Assembly District Madison Democratic Club and former Civil Court Judge and Justice of the Supreme Court, Kings County. His father also was a political leader in the Madison Club. Jordan was a 1950 graduate of St. John's Law School. Jordan died in 1995.
  This interview took place on March 19, 1989. This interview is not accompanied by a transcript.
- George Joyce, circa 1980 (Box 3, Folder 18)
- Edna Kelly, 1969-1988 (Box 3, Folder 19)
- Eugene Keogh, 1953-1987 (Box 3, Folder 20, Box 9, Cassette 27, Cassette 28)
  Eugene James Keogh was born on August 30, 1907 in Williamsburg, Brooklyn. He received his undergraduate degree from New York University and his law degree from Fordham University. He began practicing law in 1932, served in the New York State Assembly, and then was elected to the U.S. House of Representatives in 1936, serving for 15 terms until 1967. He returned to practicing law almost up until his death May 26, 1989 when he died of pneumonia.
  Jeffrey Gerson interviewed Eugene Keogh twice. The first interview took place on September 29, 1987 and includes talking while Keogh and Gerson take the elevator to the street where Keogh waits for a car service. The second interview took place on October 15, 1987.
  Both interviews took place in the law firm of Abberley, Kooiman, Marcellino and Clay at 521 Fifth Avenue in Manhattan. Both interviews are accompanied by a transcript.
  Three preservation .WAV files. Two access .mp3 files.
- Joseph Kessler, 1988 (Box 3, Folder 21, Box 9, Cassette 29)
  Joseph Kessler was born on May 18, 1919 on the Lower East Side of Manhattan. His family moved to Williamsburg in 1924 and he grew up there. Kessler was a dentist in the West Village in Manhattan. In 1948, he ran for the New York State Assembly from the 14th Assembly District in Williamsburg and Greenpoint against Edward Lentol. Kessler lost. He was the chairman of American Labor Party in Williamsburg. Kessler ran again for the New York State Assembly in 1950 and lost. Kessler died in 1996.
  This interview took place on April 18, 1988 in a coffee shop in the West Village in Manhattan. This interview is accompanied by a transcript.
- John Killens, 1987 (Box 3, Folder 22)
- Kings County Democratic Victory Dinner, 1955-1974 (Box 3, Folder 23)
- Arthur Klebanoff, 1965 (Box 3, Folder 24)
- Ed Koch, 1979-1985 (Box 3, Folder 25)
- Anna Mary Lanahan, 1977 (Box 3, Folder 26 - 29)
  These files contain photocopies of Anna Mary Lanahan's book Brooklyn's Political Life: 1898-1916.
- League of Women Voters, circa 1980 (Box 3, Folder 30)
- Joseph Lentol, 1989 (Box 3, Folder 31, Box 9, Cassette 30)
  Joseph R. Lentol was born on January 15, 1943. His mother was Matilda A. Postis and his father was New York State Assemblyman, Senator, and Supreme Court justice Edward S. Lentol. Before running for office, Lentol was Assistant District Attorney in Kings County.
  Lentol was first elected to the New York State Assembly for Assembly District (AD) 58 in 1972, running for an open seat after Assemblyman Chester Straub left to run for New York State Senator. He ran against Republican Vinny Abate in the 1972 and 1974 elections. In 1978, Roman Popadiuk ran against Lentol in the Democratic primary and Lentol won. Nick Stefanizzi, head of the local school board, ran campaigns against Lentol in the Democratic primaries in 1980 and 1982. These were close elections, but Lentol won both primaries. The 58th AD was redistricted and assigned a new number, AD 50, after the 1980 census. Fort Greene was added to this Assembly District in 1982.
  Between 1983 and 2010, Lentol did not have any Democratic primary challengers. André Soleil, a lawyer, ran against Lentol in the 2010 Democratic primary. About 6,000 votes were cast in the 2010 primary and Lentol won by a wide margin. Lentol lost to Democrat Emily Gallagher in the 2020 election. There was a large voter turnout for the 2020 election, around 20,000 people.
  During his time as a New York State Assemblyman, Lentol was the Chair of the Assembly's Committee on Codes (1992-2020), the Committee on Governmental Employees, the Committee on Governmental Operations, and the Administrative Regulations Review Commission. Lentol was also Dean of the Brooklyn Delegation of the Assembly from 2001 to 2020, coordinating efforts that called on all Brooklyn Assemblymembers to work together on projects with borough-wide implications.
  Lentol advocated for waterfront and green space preservation, criminal justice reform, and affordable housing. In 2000, Lentol was selected to be a part of the Election Modernization Task Force, which made recommendations to the State on how to increase voter registration and turnout.
  Lentol was a part of the New York Conference of Italian-American Legislators and the New York State Legislative Pilots Association.
  This interview took place on February 9, 1989 at Joseph R. Lentol's district office in Williamsburg. This interview is not accompanied by a transcript.
  Original cassette tapes are not available for research use. Access to the interview is available digitally onsite at Center for Brooklyn History's Othmer Library.
- Sebastian Leone, 1987 (Box 3, Folder 32, Box 9, Cassette 31)
  Sebastian Leone was born on December 6, 1924 on the Lower East Side of Manhattan. Leone's family moved to Brooklyn when he was one year old and he grew up in Bensonhurst. Leone's parents were from Sicily, Italy and owned a grocery store. He attended P.S. 97 David Boody Junior High School and Lafayette High School in Brooklyn and graduated from St. John's University in Queens in 1946 and St. John's University Law School in 1949.
  Leone became district leader of the United Democratic Club in the 1960s and was selected to be Brooklyn Borough President in 1970 after Abe Stark resigned. He served in that position until 1976 when he was nominated to the New York Supreme Court where he served from 1977 to 2001.
  Leone married Helene Morgenstern in 1966 and they had one son, Matthew. Leone died on November 14, 2016.
  This interview took place on October 28, 1987 at the State Supreme Court in Brooklyn. In part of the interview, Sebastian Leone discusses how Stanley Steingut as Speaker of the New York State Assembly, affected the power of political clubhouses. This interview is accompanied by a transcript.
- Arthur Levitt, Jr., 1983 (Box 3, Folder 33)
- Arthur Levitt, Jr., 1986-1989 (Box 3, Folder 34)
- David Nathaniel Licorish, 1957 (Box 3, Folder 35)
- Walter Linder, 1988 (Box 3, Folder 36, Box 9, Cassette 32, Cassette 33)
  Walter "Wally" Linder was born on May 2, 1930 in Flatbush, Brooklyn. Linder joined the Communist Party while a student at the City College of New York. He worked as a freight handler on the Baltimore and Ohio Railroad and became President of his local union in 1961.
  Linder eventually left the Communist Party and was one of the founding members of the Progressive Labor Party, which formed in 1965. Linder was also a member of the Unity Democratic Club in Brooklyn. Linder died on January 3, 2022.
  This interview took place on June 8, 1988 at a Brooklyn playground. This interview is accompanied by a transcript.
- Herbert Lupka, 1987 (Box 4, Folder 1, Box 9, Cassette 34, Cassette 35)